Guide to the Georges Lauweryns Manuscript and Printed music
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Georges Lauweryns manuscript and printed music
1899-1946
GEN MSS 899
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.08
(13 boxes)
The Georges Lauweryns Manuscript and Printed Music consists of manuscript and printed music composed by Lauweryns, and printed music of other composers owned by Lauweryns. Most music by Lauweryns consists of songs for voice and piano or voice and orchestra. Also present are piano, chamber, orchestral, and ballet music. Manuscript music by Lauweryns is in several hands, including those of copyists and possibly the composer's autograph. Some manuscripts include performance annotations or printer's markings. Many bear stamps of the Société des auteurs, compositeurs et éditeurs de musique, or are accompanied by registration forms for the Société. Music by other composers consists of songs for voice and piano by Jules Massenet, and solo piano music, orchestral works, and operas in vocal score by several early 20th-century composers, many inscribed by the composer to Lauweryns.
Lauweryns, Georges
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Georges Lauweryns
Georges Lauweryns, conductor, pianist, and composer. Lauweryns conducted at the Théâtre royal de la Monnaie, Brussels, and for operas and concerts in Paris and Monte Carlo. His brother Fernand Lauweryns was a music publisher in Brussels.
Scope and Contents
The Georges Lauweryns Manuscript and Printed Music consists of manuscript and printed music composed by Lauweryns, and printed music by others owned by Lauweryns. Most music by Lauweryns consists of songs for voice and piano or works for voice and orchestra. Also present are piano, chamber, orchestral, and ballet music. Manuscript music by Lauweryns is in several hands, including copyists and possibly the composer's autograph. Some manuscripts include performance annotations or printer's markings. Many bear stamps of the Société des auteurs, compositeurs et éditeurs de musique, or are accompanied by registration forms for the Société. Music by other composers consists of songs for voice and piano by Jules Massenet, and solo piano music, orchestral works, and operas in vocal score by several early 20th-century composers, many inscribed by the composer to Lauweryns.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Music by Georges Lauweryns, 1899-1938. II. Music by Others, 1899-1946.
Ballets -- Scores; Chamber music -- Scores; Composers -- Belgium; Operas -- Vocal scores with piano; Orchestral music -- Scores; Piano music; Songs with orchestra -- Scores; Songs with piano; Composers -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Lauweryns, Georges; Société des auteurs, compositeurs et éditeurs de musique (France)
- Music by Georges Lauweryns, 1899-1938, undated; 0.58; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Some manuscripts include draft fragments of unidentified works. Some dates are from stamps or accompanying registration forms of the Société des auteurs, compositeurs et éditeurs de musique. Uniform titles have not been determined. Contents of sets of parts have not been verified.
  - À Sinaïa, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    For violin, cello, and piano. Manuscript score.
  - Adieux, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    For voice and piano. Words by Jean Bartholoni. Manuscript score.
  - And I also, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    For voice and orchestra. Manuscript piano-conductor part.
  - L'aveu permis, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For voice and orchestra. Words by Madame Desbordes-Valmore. Manuscript score and parts.
  - Ballade des trois chevaliers qui sont morts de faim, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For voice and piano. Words by Alfred Mabille. Manuscript score.
  - Le ballet des chats, undated (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 6)
    For orchestra. Manuscript score.
  - Cantate patriotique, undated (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    For chorus and orchestra. Printed vocal score and parts (Brussels: Maison Lauweryns Éditeur).
  - Célimène, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    For piano. Manuscript music.
  - C'est la saison d'aimer, c1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    For orchestra. Printed piano-conductor score and parts (Brussels: Fernand Lauweryns Éditeur, c1919).
  - C'est le plus beau chant d'amour, 1936 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    For voice and piano. Words by Félix Chevrier. Manuscript score, signed and dated at Nice.
  - Le chant des Vosgiens, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    For voice and piano. Words by Félix Chevrier. Manuscript score.
  - Crépescule, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    For voice and piano. Words by Valère Sille. Manuscript score.
  - Il destino, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    For violin, cello, bass, and piano. Manuscript parts.
  - Emotive!, 1924 November 4 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    For piano. Manuscript, dated at Nice.
  - En forme de menuet, c1922 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    For orchestra. Printed score (Nice: Paul Decourcelle, c1922).
  - Encore un baiser..., 1924 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Les epaves, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    For voice and piano. Words by Félix Chevrier. Printed score (Paris: Editions Maurice Brisville).
  - Fanita, c1909 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    For piano. Printed music (Brussels: J. B. Katto, c1909).
  - Fleur d'automne, 1905 July 2 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 19)
    For voice and orchestra. Words by Lucien Solvay. Manuscript score and parts, signed.
  - Fleurs de Belgique, 1927 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    For voice and piano. Words by Félix Chevrier. Manuscript score, signed and dated at Paris.
  - Flirt à Monte Carlo, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Two versions: for piano, manuscript, with printed cover (Nice: Delrieu, undated); and for violin and piano, manuscript score.
  - Gloire à la nature, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    For 2 voices and piano. Words by Gaston Sirejacob. Printed score (Paris: Heugel, undated).
  - Hopjes en Hopjes, undated (Box 13 (Oversize), Folder 23-24)
    Ballet. Manuscript score, 2 copies, and manuscript part for violin I.
  - Hymne Belge du Congo, 1927 (Box 13 (Oversize), Folder 25)
  - Larmes d'amour, 1905 July 27-1912 June 10 (Box 13 (Oversize), Folder 26)
  - La legende de Saint Nicolas, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    For orchestra. Manuscript piano-conductor part.
  - Marche Vosgienne, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    For orchestra. Manuscript piano-conductor part, 2 versions, and manuscript part for saxophone.
  - Méditation, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    For organ or harmonium. Printed music (Brussels: Fernand Lauwerysn, 1924), dated at Nice.
  - Mélodies. Ta beauté, c1905 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    For voice and piano. Words by Lucien Solvay. Printed score (Paris: Heugel, c1905).
  - Mélodies. Ta beauté, 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    For voice and orchestra. Words by Lucien Solvay. 2 sets of manuscript scores and parts.
  - Mon toucher, 1922 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Ode à l'Italie, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
    For voice and orchestra. Words by Ernesta Stern. Manuscript score, vocal score, and parts.
  - Offrande, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Words by Ernesta Stern. Versions for voice, violin, and piano, manuscript score; and orchestra, manuscript score and violin parts.
  - Opéra-tango, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    For unspecified instruments. Manuscript piano-conductor part.
  - Le pékinois, 1927 August 30 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    For voice and piano. Words by Félix Chevrier. Manuscript score, dated at Paris.
  - Petit frère est guéri, 1927 September 1 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Petit marchand, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - [Petites mélodies]. Près d'un berceau, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    For voice and piano. Words by Lucien Solvay. Printed score (Brusseles: Fernand Lauwerysn, undated).
  - Pie Jesu, 1899 April 5 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    For solo voice, chorus, and organ. Manuscript score and parts.
  - Le printemps passa, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    For instrumental ensemble. Manuscript piano-conductor part.
  - Redis-moi toujours, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Words by Félix Chevrier. Two versions: for voice and piano, manuscript score; and for voice and orchestra, manuscript parts.
  - Redis-moi toujours, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    For voice and piano. Score. Words by Félix Chevrier. Printed score (Paris: Maurice Brisville, undated).
  - Le reve de chérubin, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    For violin and piano. Manuscript score.
  - Roman d'amour, 1909 May (Box 5, Folder 47)
    For voice an orchestra. Manuscript score, signed and dated at Brussels.
  - Solitude, 1904 August 27 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    For voice and piano. Words by Albert Bonjean. Manuscript score, dated at Brussels.
  - Sonata quasi fantasia, 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    For cello and piano. Manuscript cello part, 2 versions, one dated 1938, Lyon.
  - Tendre passion, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Vanita, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    For voice and piano. Words by Lucien Solvay. Manuscript score.
  - Violon de lune, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
    For voice and piano. Words by Albert Giraud. Manuscript score.
- Music by Others, c1899-c1946, undated; Series II; 0.5; (6 boxes)
  Uniform titles have not been determined.
  Arranged alphabetically by name and title.
  - Albéniz, Isaac. Iberia, c1907 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    For piano. Printed music (Madrid: Unión musical española, c1907), annotated in manuscript with a ballet scenario.
  - Beydts, Louis. Mélodies, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Le passé qui file For voice and piano. Printed score (Paris: Magasin Musica, Pierre Schneider, undated).
  - Beydts, Louis. Moineau, c1931 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    Opera. Printed vocal score (Brussels: Salabert, c1931).
  - Beydts, Louis. Trois chansons de Louis Codet. La flûte verte, undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
    For voice and piano. Printed score (Paris: Magasin Musica, Pierre Schneider, undated).
  - Bréville, Pierre de. Eros vainqueur, c1910 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    Opera. Printed vocal score (Paris: Rouart, Lerolle, c1910).
  - Buffin, Victor. Kaatje, c1913 (Box 11, Folder 58)
    Opera. Printed vocal score (Paris: Max Eschig, c1913).
  - Coppola, Piero. Scherzo fantastique, undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
    For orchestra. Printed miniature score (Paris: Editions Max Eschig, undated).
  - Ganne, Louis. Illys, c1910 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    For orchestra. Score (Paris: Costallat, c1910)
  - Hirchmann, Henri. La reine de Thyrma, c1946 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    Opera. Printed vocal score (Paris: Choudens, c1946).
  - Lauweryns, E., fils. V'la c'que c'est d'être savant, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
    For voice and piano. Printed score (Brussels: Schott, undated).
  - Lieth, Lenore. Songs, c1923 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    For voice and piano. Printed score (Philadelphia: Presser, c1923).
  - Lorenzi, P. Marraine!, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    For voice and orchestra. Manuscript vocal score and part for violin I/conductor.
  - Massenet, Jules. Songs for voice and piano, c1899-c1913, undated (Box 7, Folder 65-67)
    Printed scores:
    L'âme des fleurs. Version in C major. (Paris: Quinzard, undated).
    C'est l'amour. Version for contralto. (Paris: Heugel, c1908).
    Expressions lyriques. En voyage. Version for soprano. (Paris: Heugel, 1913).
    La gavotte de Puyjoli. Version for one voice. (Paris: Heugel, undated).
    La lettre. Version in F major. (Paris: Heugel, c1907).
    Les mains. Version for soprano. (Paris: Heugel, c1899).
    Mélodies. Avril est amoureux. 2 versions: mezzo soprano or baritone; tenor (Paris: Heugel, c1900).
    [Mélodies]. Éveil. Verison for mezzo soprano or baritone. (Paris: Heugel, c1906).
    [Mélodies]. La vie d'une rose. (Paris: Girod, undated).
    Oh! Si les fleurs ayient des yeux. 3 versions: mezzo soprano or baritone; soprano; tenor. (Paris: Heugel, c1903).
    Les oiselets. Verison for mezzo soprano or baritone. (Paris: Hartmann, undated).
    Rondel de la belle au bois. (Paris: Heugel, c1900)
    Sérénade du passant. Verison for mezzo soprano or baritone. (Paris: Hartmann, undated).
    Si vous vouliez bien me le dire. Version for baritone. (Paris: Heugel, c1907).
  - Pottellet, Marie. Première valse, undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
    For piano. Printed music (Brussels: J. B. Katto, undated).
  - Pratella, Francesco Balilla. Romagna, c1920 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    For orchestra; arranged for piano. Printed music (Bologna: Pizzi, c1920).
  - Sjögren, Emil. [Sonata, violin, piano. no. 5], 1918 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    Printed music (Stockholm: Musikaliska Konstföreningen, 1914).
  - Strauss, Richard. Tod und Verklärung, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
    For orchestra. Printed score (Munich: Jos. Aibl, undated).
  - Wallner, Léopold. Duexième sonate romantique, c1909 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    For piano. Printed music (Brussels: Schott, c1909).
  - Wouters, Adolphe F. Gammes majeurs et mineurs en tierces, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
    For piano. Printed music (Brussels: Breitkopf & Härtel, undated).